Jezebel Productions records SSC.MS.00534
Sophia Smith Collection
Jezebel Productions records
1970-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
Jezebel Productions
SSC.MS.00534
25 boxes (32.25 linear feet)
1930 Gigabytes (8686 digital files)
Film production company. Collection includes original film and video footage and outtakes, scripts, production notes, interviews, catalogs from film festivals where Jezebel films were shown; and books, articles and film reviews by Andrea Weiss. Some records included in this collection are not the works of Jezebel Productions, such as materials related to the making of "Before Stonewall," co-produced by Greta Schiller.
Biographical / Historical
Jezebel Productions is an independent film production company, founded in 1984 by Greta Schiller and Andrea Weiss. The company has been based in New York City and London since 1998. Films include International Sweethearts of Rhythm (1986), Tiny and Ruby: Hell Divin' Women (1988), and Maxine Sullivan: Love To Be In Love (1991), a trilogy about women in jazz; Woman of the Wolf (1994); Paris Was A Women (1995); A Bit of Scarlet (1997); Seed of Sarah (1998); The Man Who Drove With Mandela (1998); Escape To Life: The Erika and Klaus Mann Story (2000); I Live At Ground Zero (2002); and Recall Florida (2003). Prior to founding Jezebel Productions, Schiller was Producer/Director and Weiss served as Research Director for Before Stonewall (1985), an Emmy Award- winning documentary that traced the social, political, and cultural development of the gay and lesbian community in New York City.
Greta Schiller has produced and directed documentries for European Television and for MayaVision International, and has been awarded numerous grants and prizes for her work, including the first Fulbright Arts Fellowship in Film. Her films are held in many prestigious collections around the world.
Andrea Weiss earned a B.A. in English and Women's Studies from the State Univerisity of New York at Binghamton in 1977, an M.A. in English and Women's Studies from the University of Oklahoma in 1981, and a Ph.D. in history from Rutgers University. She has taught women's studies, history, film studies, and film/video production at a variety of institutions. She is currently a Professor in the Film/Video Program of the Department of Media and Communication Arts at the City College of New York, where she has taught since 2003.
In addition to making independent films, she is the author of Vampires and Violets: Lesbians in Film (1993), Paris Was A Woman: Portraits from the Left Bank (1995)--which formed the basis for the Jezebel productions documentary of the same name-- and In the Shadow of Magic Mountain: The Erika and Klaus Mann Story (2008), about the children of Thomas Mann. She is also the co-author with Greta Schiller of Before Stonewal l (1987). Weiss has written many book chapters, articles and film reviews, and has been awarded numerous fellowships and grants. She has taught at the International Film and Photo Workshops, New York University, the City University of New York, and the National Film and Television School of Great Britain.
Scope and Contents
Various documents relating to Jezebel films are included, as are books, articles and film reviews by Andrea Weiss. Original footage and outtakes consist of a variety of audiovisual formats including film, video and audio tapes, digital production files, still images, aduio and transcripts. Some materials in the collection are not the works of Jezebel Productions, such as materials related to the film Before Stonewall, co-produced by Greta Schiller.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
This collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
Original audiovisual materials are closed; research copies must be made.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Greta Schiller and Andrea Weiss began donating the records of Jezabel Productions to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2005.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Documentary films--United States--Production and direction; Feminism and motion pictures; Gays in motion pictures; Independent filmmakers -- Biography -- Sources; Lesbians in motion pictures; Motion pictures -- Production and direction; Lesbian community -- France -- Paris -- History; Paris (France) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century; Women artists -- France -- Paris -- History -- 20th century; Women intellectuals -- France -- Paris -- Biography; Women authors -- History -- 20th century; Women in motion pictures -- History -- Sources; Schiller, Greta; Weiss, Andrea; articles; Audiotapes; Books; correspondence; DVD video discs; memorabilia; Motion pictures; Newspapers; Posters; press releases; Publicity; Reviews; Scripts; Sound recordings; Videotapes; Writings; Computer media; Electronic records; Jezebel Productions; Schiller, Greta
- 2018 accession, 1970-2017
  Scope and Contents
  This accession includes records of film production, business records, one film reel and VHS tape copies of films, digital production files.
  - Woman of the Wolf: cast and crew information, press kit, publicity, and transcript, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Maxine: correspondence, press, releases, stills, and transcript, 1979-1993 (Box 1)
  - Paris Was a Woman: correspondence, press, and television proposal, 1992-1999 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1977-2002 (Box 1)
  - Greetings from Washington DC: correspondence, press, and project proposal, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Research for film never made, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Wedding Bell Blues: Screenplay, 1991 (Box 1)
  - No Dinosaurs in Heaven: signed releases, 2008-2010 (Box 1)
  - Margaret/Margarita: synopsis, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Escape to Life: The Erika and Klaus Mann Story: correspondence, press, and project proposal, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Before Stonewall book proposal, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Interview with Greta Schiller, approximately 1984 (Box 1)
  - Library poetry education program, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous contract agreements, 1989-2004 (Box 1)
  - Berlin Film Festival papers, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Vampires & Violets: correspondence and press, approximately 1995-2008 (Box 1)
  - In The Shadow of Magic Mountain: correspondence, approximately 1997-2008 (Box 1)
  - Seed of Sarah: correspondence, approximately 1997-2008 (Box 1)
  - The Marion Lake Story: correspondence, 2013 (Box 2)
  - Proposal samples: Paris Was a Woman, Reno On The Road, Escape To Life, and Plum Island, 1995-2002 (Box 2)
  - Ljubljana, Slovenia Pride papers, 2017 (Box 2)
  - New York Times articles on Before Stonewall, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Maxine: press, publicity, and video rating guide, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Woman of the Wolf: publicity and mailing list, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Interview with Greta Schiller and Andrea Weiss, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Cinema Guild contracts, 1994-2001 (Box 2)
  - Reviews of various films, 1985-1994 (Box 2)
  - Photos of Janet Reno gubernatorial campaign, 2002 (Box 2)
  - I Lived At Ground Zero: correspondence and proposal, 2001-2003 (Box 2)
  - Sweethearts of Rhythm: correspondence, press, photos, and reviews, 1985-1988 (Box 2)
  - Tiny and Ruby: correspondence, press, photos, transcript, and reviews, 1985-2000 (Box 2)
  - Seed of Sarah: press, photos, transcript, 1995-1998 (Box 2)
  - Escape to Life: photos, music cue sheet, transcript, 2000-2002 (Box 2)
  - The Man Who Drove with Mandela: GLAAD nomination, music cue sheet, transcript, 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Paris Was a Woman: clearances, music cue sheet, narration cue sheet, transcript, 1996-1998 (Box 2)
  - A Bit of Scarlet: reviews, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Before Stonewall: reviews, 1984 (Box 2)
  - "Mother film" papers, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - "Mother film": correspondence, grant applications, 1978 (Box 3)
  - The Marion Lake Story and Andrea Weiss' writings: digital files (HD #18), 2007-2014; 1 items (1 external hard drive); 240 Gigabytes (3,085 files) (Box 3)
    Files copied from backup hard drive (HD #18) include all materials for the film "The Marion Lake Story" by Greta Schiller (video, audio, transcripts, still images). Also has one folder of Andrea Weiss' writings.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access. Note that some of this content was created using the video production program FinalCut Pro; and Special Collections cannot provide the required software to access file formats dependent on specific software.
  - No Dinosaurs in Heaven: digital files (HD #6), 2009-2015; 1 items (1 external hard drive); 799 Gigabytes (419 files) (Box 4)
    Files copied from backup hard drive (HD #6) including video production files for No Dinosaurs in Heaven (continued from HD 3) with Grand Canyon footage, Interview of Steve Newton; Beyond Stonewall UK trailer; and the Why Study Science extra.; GC Stills (from David Biehl) See attached file list for details.
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access. Note that some of this content was created using the video production program FinalCut Pro and will require that program to access. Special Collections cannot provide the required software to access all file formats.
  - No Dinosaurs in Heaven: digital files (HD #8), 2006-2011; 1 items (1 external hard drive); 94 Gigabytes (830 digital files) (Box 4)
    Files copied from backup hard drive (HD #8). Includes video production files for No Dinosaurs in Heaven. Also includes transcripts (Word files), Powerpoint presentations, and still images. See attached file list for details.
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access. Note that some of this content was created using the video production program FinalCut Pro; and Special Collections cannot provide the required software to access all file formats.
  - No Dinosaurs in Heaven and other projects: digital files (HD #9), 2008-2009; 1 items (1 external hard drive); 289 Gigabytes (2,372 digital files) (Box 4)
    Files copied from backup hard drive (Jezebel HD, #9) including video production files for No Dinosaurs in Heaven, with Grand Canyon footage; plus other projects. See attached file list for details.
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access. Note that some of this content was created using the video production program FinalCut Pro. Special Collections cannot provide required software to access all file formats.
  - Various Jezebel projects: digital files, 2008-2009; 1 items (1 external hard drive); 113 Gigabytes (207 digital files) (Box 4)
    Files copied from backup hard drive (Tekserve "A") containing video production files for "OSG Project; "Beyond Stonewall"; "Poems from the Water's Edge"; "Grand Canyon"; and one folder titled "Greta other" See attached file list for details.
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access.
  - Various Jezebel projects: digital files (HD #14), 2006-2014; 1 items (1 external hard drive); 25.4 Gigabytes (275 files) (Box 4)
    Files copied from backup hard drive(HD #14) including video production files for various film projects: HD #14. "NYCC + Chinese Folk Dance Co; Lunar New Year Projections; Seed stills; Beats Archive; Same view, Different Day; Escape DVD extras; also includes "photos burned to CD for Univ Chicago Press". See attached file list for details.
  - "Jezebel Press Kits for ETL": digital files, December 2000; 1 items (1 3.5 inch floppy disk); 0.000364 Gigabytes (1 disk image and 11 extracted files) (Box 4)
    Files copied from floppy disk, include Lotus WordPro files for press kit for "ETL" [Escape to Life?]. See attached file list for details.
    This content was received from the donor in digital form and is not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request copies.
    Note: Special Collections cannot provide the required software to access all file formats. These files were created using Lotus WordPro software.
  - Tiny and Ruby negative stills, 1988 (Box 4)
  - "NSCE PSAs Disc 2" DVD, approximately 2000 (Box 4)
  - "The Weiss Family Album" VHS, approximately 1986 (Box 5)
  - "The Man Who Drove With Mandela" VHS, approximately 1998-2000 (Box 5)
  - "Nightwatch" VHS, 1986 (Box 5)
  - "International Sweethearts of Rhythm: work in progress" VHS, approximately 1984-1988 (Box 5)
  - "Women of Wolf" VHS, approximately 1994-1996 (Box 5)
  - "Before Stonewall" VHS, approximately 1984-1986 (Box 5)
  - Paris Was a Woman poster, approximately 1992-1997 (Mapcase flat file)